Finding Aid for Ann Arbor (Mich.) Fire Department records, 1850-1962
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Ann Arbor (Mich.) Fire Department records 1850-1962
Ann Arbor (Mich.). Fire Department.
2.5 linear feet (in 3 boxes) and 8 oversize volumes
861042 Cc 2;CC Out. Vol.
Minute books of the Fire Department and of related voluntary fire companies; also other administrative records, including records of expenditures and salaries, and records detailing individual fires; and record books, 1876-1899, of city poor relief (then administered by the Fire Department); also photograph.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The bulk of these records came from the Ann Arbor Fire Department (donor no. 7302 ) in February 1986. Additional records were received from different donors (donor nos. 4338 and 593 ).
No further additions to the records are expected.
The record group is open to research.
Prior to the establishment of a city fire department in 1854, volunteer fire companies did the work of putting out fires in Ann Arbor, Michigan. One of these, the Ann Arbor Fire Co. No. 2, was organized in 1837. This later became Eagle Fire Company No. 2. The names of other companies included the Defiance Hood and Ladder Company and the Mayflower Fire Engine Company. The companies continued to do their work up into the 1880s.
In the later part of the nineteenth century, the fire department also had responsibility for administering poor relief in the city.
The record group includes an early minute book of the fire department as well as minute books of various volunteer fire companies in the city. There are, in addition, scattered administrative records, including records of fires in the city, 1899-1962, and records of the poor relief administered by the department. These poor relief volumes include the name of the recipient, the amount, and the items purchased. Also included are the names of the individuals who funded the relief fund.
Subjects:
Fire departments--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Public welfare--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Defiance Hook and Ladder Company, No. 1 (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Eagle Fire Department (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Ann Arbor (Mich.). Fire Dept.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Ann Arbor (Mich.). Fire Dept.; Fire fighters.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Minute Books
  - Fire Department minute book 1854-1888 (Box 1)
    (includes organizational records relating to merger of fire companies into fire department)
  - Defiance Hood and Ladder Company (volunteer fire company)
    - Minute book July 19 1955 (Box 1)
    - Minute book 1877-1882 (donor no. 4338) (Box 1)
  - Eagle Fire Department (volunteer fire company) minute book August 22, 2005 (Box 1)
    (donor no. 593)
  - Mayflower Fire Engine Company minute book 1866-1869 (Box 1)
- Administrative Records
  - Budget Summary sheets 1923-1946 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence 1912-1944 (Box 1)
  - Expenditures and Salaries 1890-1939
    - 1890-1939, 5 volumes (Box 1)
    - 1939-1954, 1 volume (Box 2)
  - Fire Hydrant Installation and Location record book 1907-1945 (Box 2)
  - Fire Loss Figures 1939-1952 (Box 2)
  - Inventories of Equipment 1945-1946 (Box 2)
  - Newspaper Clippings 1924-1952 (Box 2)
  - Record Books of Fires
    - 1899-1926, 3 volumes (Box 2)
    - 1906-1926, 2 volumes (Box 2)
    - 1927-1930 (Volume 1)
    - 1931-1935 (Volume 2)
    - 1935-1938 (Volume 3)
    - 1938-1943 (Volume 4)
    - 1944-1951 (Volume 5)
    - 1951-1956 (Volume 6)
    - 1957-1959 (Volume 7)
    - 1959-1962 (Volume 8)
    - Additional Records of Fires 1941-1955 (Box 2)
      (some overlap with outsize volumes)
  - Miscellaneous Papers 1906-1944 (Box 2)
  - Photograph of members of the department, 1900 (Box 2)
- Poor Relief
  (administered by the fire department)
  - Record books
    - 1876-1893, 5 volumes (Box 3)
      (records for 1894-1896 not received)
    - 1897-1899 (Box 3)
  - Receipt book 1879-1880 (Box 3)